Archana Y. Gajbhiye

Department of Biotechnology Sir Padampat Singhania University, Bhatewar, Udaipur- 313601 Rajasthan (India)

| Mob: 09610252142 | E-mail: archana.yg@gmail.com



Profile

A dedicated, motivated, adaptable and hardworking professional, with over 20 years' experience in teaching, research and industry in the area of microbiology and microbial biotechnology. I am serving the position of HoD in the Department of Biotechnology at SPSU since 2011. I have gained extensive experience and skills of teaching, research and administration through my previous and current job profile. I believe that my experience and expertise in academia & research will be beneficial in delivering the fruitful outcomes of your organization.

Work Experience: 21 Years

Teaching Experience: 15 Years

- 1. Sir Padampat Singhania University, Udaipur-313601 (India) Assistant Professor, Department of Biotechnology, from 2008 - present Role and Responsibilities
 - HoD, Department of Biotechnology since 2011.
 - Teaching theory and laboratory subjects to undergraduate and Post Graduate students (B. Tech)
 - Supervise Ph. D scholars
 - Developing and updating the curriculum.
 - Devising academic plans (Teaching-Learning) for each semester (Outcome based education system OBE)
 - Monitoring student development (Progress evaluation, Mentorship etc.).
 - Member of Board of Studies, Academic Council and other academic bodies of the University
 - Interim IQAC Coordinator since March 2022. Organize meetings of IQAC, AQAR preparation and submission etc.
 - Coordinator of cultural events.
- 2. P.G. Dept. of Microbiology, RTM Nagpur University, Nagpur, India Lecture (Contract Basis), Sept. 2006 Mar 2007 and Sept 2007- Mar 2008 Role and Responsibilities
 - Teach and supervise the lab experiments of Environmental Microbiology to the students of Post-Graduation degree programme (M. Sc. Microbiology).
- 3. Rajiv Gandhi Biotechnology Center, RTM Nagpur University, Nagpur, India Lecture (Contract Basis), Sept 2007- Mar 2008 and Sept 2008 Oct 2008 Role and Responsibilities
 - Teach theory subjects and laboratory experiments to the students of Post-Graduation degree programme (M. Sc. Biotechnology).

Research Experience: 3 Years 9 Months

1. Central Institute for Cotton Research, Nagpur, India

Research Associate, From August 5, 2003 to December 31, 2004

- Worked under the NATP project "Development of Bt-transgenic cotton".
- Laboratory work on developing the protocols for performing *Agrobacterium* Mediated transformations of cotton explants.
- Record keeping of observations and results.

2. Central Institute for Cotton Research, Nagpur, India

Senior Research Fellow, October 12, 2000 to March 31, 2003

- Worked under the NATP-CGP project "Induction of *para*-nodules in cotton plant, using nitrogen fixing bacterium *Azorhizobium caulinodans*".
- Laboratory work on developing the protocols for inducing para nodules in roots of cotton seedlings.
- Record keeping of observations and results.

Industrial Experience: 2 Years 2 Months

1. H. jules & Co. Ltd. (Injectable Division), Nagpur, India.

Quality Control Department

Quality Control Chemist, From January 12, 2000 to October 10, 2000

- Sampling of raw material, in process material and finished product.
- Microbiological and biochemical analysis of the samples according to IP, USP and BP.
- Recording the results and reporting to the Manager, QC Department.

2. Magrul Mills Ltd., Nagpur

Investigator, Quality Control, From September 16, 1998 to January 10, 2000

- Sampling of raw material (Cotton lint), in process material and finished product (Yarn).
- Analysis of the samples (Strength, Humidity etc.).
- Recording the results and reporting to the Manager, QC Department.

Education

Ph.D., Microbiology March 2009 Department of Microbiology, R.T.M. Nagpur University, Nagpur, India Awarded Rajiv Gandhi National **JRF & SRF** for Ph.D

Master of Science (M.Sc.) in Microbiology Summer-1998 66.00% Department of Microbiology, Nagpur University, Nagpur, India

Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.) Summer-1996 69.33%

Nagpur University, Nagpur, India

RESEARCH

Scopus/ Orcid ID: https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8596-3994

Google Scholar link:

https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=idKQySMAAAAJ&hl=en&oi=ao

• Research Papers: 17

- 1. Dongre AB, Bhandarkar M, Sawant R, Kharbikar L and **Gajbhiye A** (2007) Assessment of genetic diversity of cotton cultivars (*Gossypium Spp.*) by ISSR and microsatellite markers. *Asian Journal of Microbiology, Biotechnology and Environmental Sciences*, 9(1):31-36.
- 2. **Gajbhiye A**, Bhandarkar M, Dongre AB and Meshram S (2007) Genetic diversity evaluation of *Bacillus* isolates using randomly amplified polymorphic DNA molecular marker. *Romanian Biotechnological Letters*, 12(3): 3277-3286.
- 3. **Gajbhiye A**, Rai AR, Meshram SU and Dongre AB (2010) Isolation, evaluation and characterization of *Bacillus subtilis* from cotton rhizospheric soil with biocontrol activity against *Fusarium oxysporum*. *World J of Microbiology and Biotechnology*, 26: 1187-1194.
- 4. Bhavani M, Chowdary GV, David M and **Archana G** (2012) Screening, isolation and biochemical characterization of novel lipase producing bacteria from soil samples, *International Journal of Biological Engineering*. 2012, 2(2): 18-22.
- 5. Kumar P, Sharma R and **Gajbhiye A** (2015) Characterization of biosurfactant from *Bacillus* isolates as antifungal agent. *Indo Global Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences*, 5(2): 117-123.
- 6. Varghese J and **Gajbhiye A** (2016) Purification and characterization of trypsin inhibitor protein from seeds of *Momordica dioica*. *Asian Journal of Pharmaceutical and Clinical Research*, 2016, 9(3): 335-339.
- 7. Varghese J and **Gajbhiye A** (2016) Characterization of protein from *Momordica dioica* seeds for trypsin inhibitory activity and its mass spectrometric analysis. *J de Afrikana*, 3(2): 214-224.
- 8. Nagda V, **Gajbhiye A** and Kumar D (2017) Isolation and characterization of endophytic fungi from *Calotropis procera* for their antioxidant activity. *Asian Journal of Pharmaceutical and Clinical Research*, 10(3): 254-258.
- 9. Bhatnagar P, Vyas D, Sinha SK and **Gajbhiye A** (2017) HPLC method for simultaneous estimation of drug release of levodopa and carbidopa in entacapone, levodopa and carbidopa tablets. *International Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences and Research*, 8(3): 1091-1101.
- 10. Bhatnagar P, Vyas D, Sinha SK and **Gajbhiye A** (2017) HPLC method for estimation of drug release of entacapone in entacapone, levodopa and carbidopa tablets. *International Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences and Research*, 8(4): 1734-1743.
- 11. Nagda V, **Gajbhiye A** and Kumar D (2017) *In vitro* antioxidant and alpha amylase inhibition activity of plant associated fungi isolated from *Catharanthus roseus*. *International Journal of Pharmacy and Biological Sciences*, 7(3):114-122.
- 12. Kumar D., **Gajbhiye A.**, Nagda V. and Arora A. (2018). Antibacterial activity of zinc sulphate and silver nitrate against human pathogenic bacteria. *World Journal of Pharmaceutical Research*, 7(5):1427-1435.
- 13. Kumar D., **Gajbhiye A.**, Nagda V. and Arora A. (2018). Characterization of root extracts of *Withania somnifera* and effect of zinc sulphate and silver nitrate on antibacterial activity against certain human pathogenic bacteria. *International Journal of Pharmacy and Biological Sciences*, 8(4):682-689.
- 14. Kumar D., **Gajbhiye A.**, Nagda V. and Arora A. (2020) Effect of zinc sulphate on antimicrobial activity of *Clitorea ternatea*. **Research Journal of Chemistry and Environment**, 24(2):1-6.

- 15. Rastogi, P. M., Kumar, N., Sharma, A., Vyas, D. and **Gajbhiye**, **A**. (2020). Sustainability of Aluminium Oxide Nanoparticles Blended Mahua Biodiesel to the Direct Injection Diesel Engine Performance and Emission Analysis. **Pollution**, 6(1): 25-33. DOI: 10.22059/poll.2019.283884.633.
- 16. Rathore M., Vyas D., Chakrabarti T., **Gajbhiye A.**, Chamoli M. and Rathore M.S. (2021). To survey and analyse the soil samples for physicochemical and biochemical parameters from different villages of (Nagaur district) Rajasthan, India. **International journal of multidisciplinary research and development**. 8(12): 50-55.
- 17. Mahala KR, Vyas D, Chakrabarti T, **Gajbhiye A.** (2022) Assessment of Pesticides use and Heavy Metals Analysis of Surface and Ground Water Sources by Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy at Nagaur Region, Rajasthan (India). **International Journal of Mechanical Engineering**. 7(1): 7079-7089.

• Chapters in Books: 01

- 1. **Gajbhiye A**. Microbial fuel cells for bioenergy production through wastewater treatment. *In*: Biotechnological tools for genetic resources. (Ed. Deka PC). Daya Publishing House, New Delhi. pp. 347-372. 2016.
- Published Abstracts: 17

• Ph. D Students Supervised: 03

- 1. Student's name: Jinitha Varghese, Topic: Purification and characterization of serine protease inhibitor from *Momordica dioica*. 2017.
- 2. Student's name: Vipin Nagda, Topic: Characterization of Bioactive Compounds from Fungi Associated with Certain Medicinal Plants. 2019.
- 3. Student's name: Dinesh Kumar, Topic: Antimicrobial synergistic effects of certain metal and medicinal plant extracts against pathogenic bacteria. 2020.

• B. Tech Students research projects supervised: 14

• Research Projects Sanctioned: 01

Project entitled, "Application of polymer matrix of starch nanoparticles for food packaging" sanctioned for funding of Rs. 15000/- by DST Rajasthan under the Students Project Program-2017-18.

Workshops/Seminars/FDPs

Seminars, Conferences, Symposia, Workshops, Trainings etc. attended: 18

Faculty Development Programmes (FDP) attended: 07

Professional Memberships: 02

- 1. Life member, Association of Microbiologists of India, India (Membership ID: 4748-2018)
- 2. Life Member, Global Biotech Forum, Nagpur, Maharashtra, India.

References

1. Prof. Shrihari Honwad

President,

Sir Padampat Singhania University

Bhatewar, Udaipur-313601

Mob: 09897620624

E-mail: shrihari.honwad@spsu.ac.in

2. Prof. P. C. Deka

Former Vice Chancellor Sir Padampat Singhania University Bhatewar, Udaipur-313601

Mob: 09799396289

E-mail: deka.pradip47@gmail.com

3. Dr. Arti Shanware

Director

Rajiv Gandhi Biotechnology Centre

L.I.T. premises, Amravati Road, RTM Nagpur University

Nagpur-440033, Maharashtra, India

Mob: 09823018963

E-mail: artishanware@gmail.com

Udaipur 18.05.2022

Archana Gajbhiye